you
hello
here everyone
Desha Janya
Abhinav
I thought you weren't going to join
Abhishek, Ahima, Dharam, Ashish, Ashwin
Mangeem was also not going to join
Dheeraj, Pramod, Tejal, Muniswara, Rohit, Sambet, Shashank
Asha is important
That's the dedication I am personally looking for
one day
Cool then let me share my screen
and
to be honest
I didn't really do much
on the internet front
but
let's see
let me know
once my screen is
visible
we'll wait for another minute
and then we'll begin
and first of all thank you
thank you for joining on a non-class day
and
folks who haven't joined
they can obviously watch the recording
and tomorrow before starting the lecture
I'll go through
whatever doubts they may have
so it's a mistake on my end
so I'll take care
of it
right
Abhishek
it's evening
right
cool then
I think
considering
we got a head start
yesterday
so
we'll probably end the lecture also a little early
today
I'll try to make sure
if we can enter
the lecture a little early
cool then
it's 9.05 let's begin
so I'll start from the very start
obviously the part that we had covered
in the last class
I'll quickly go over through that
and in case any of those
things is not clear to you
you can ask me again
just a quick show of hands
if the screen quality and everything is fine
yes
yes right
in case the screen
quality reduces
which I hope it not
let me know we'll wait for a while and then
we'll begin
cool then let's begin
so
let's start from the
very start I'll assume that
we didn't have much talk
yesterday
so if you remember
we discussed in the last class that
we haven't installed JavaScript
anywhere
it's been just there
either we've been using it in our browser
either we are simply creating
an HTML file and directly
writing JavaScript in the
script app
so we haven't really installed
JavaScript
so the answer is have you installed JavaScript
obviously the answer is no
so you cannot really do much with JavaScript
alone as we discussed in the last class
and
JavaScript just gives you
the logic part of things
so let's say just
gives you just the logic
that's it nothing else
so basically if it just gives me the logic
which means
it's give me if a statement
for
new
variable
etc
so it just give me
these things that I can build my logic
but I cannot really build
out a feature feature out of it
so it is
sort of like a headless
I cannot do much with it
so which is why
we
super boost somehow
JavaScript with something called an
environment
so
some of the
environments that you may have
worked on
would like to know some of the
environments that you have worked on
with JavaScript
one is definitely
browser correct
what's the other one
node
correct
so we have browser and node
and there are couple more
but we will focus on browsers and
node environment
so whenever I were to pair
JavaScript with browser
I'm able to do manipulate
DOM
it does something now I'm able to manipulate
DOM I can play around
add tags, remove tags
and change values
and here to events and do a lot of other things
if I were to do it with
node
it opens a lot of those
be it on the back
and front
so likewise
so basically JavaScript alone
isn't much but when I
when I join JS
plus
environment
then it is like
build
apps
be it front end app, back end app
desktop app or anything
so long story short
you cannot really do much with JavaScript
if you were to add it with some sort of environment
you can do a lot with it
just to give you an idea as I mentioned in the last class also
something as trivial as console.log
it is also not present there
in JavaScript for that also you
rely on some sort of environment
which lets you do that
and all of this was made possible
simply because of something called V8 engine
it is a
Google's open source high performance
JavaScript and WebAssembly
engine
so first of all V8 engine was
introduced
in Chrome
and later
it got open
source with Chromium
so you may have heard of this term
let's say Brave or Edge
all of these are Chromium based
web browser
so Chromium is an open source repository
and on top of it they are building
their own features like Microsoft has built
this thing
on its own engine
but all of it ultimately takes inspiration
from Chromium because Chromium has
internally it is powered by
V8 engine and that V8 engine
was a game changer
because if you think about it there are a lot of other
languages out there
but why is it that JavaScript was the only
for which the trajectory went like this
and now if you are a JavaScript
developer you can get employed
anywhere, anywhere in the sense
across any domain
so let's try
out something
for frontend
if you were to have
JS plus
browsers
for BE
you have JS
plus node
for
mobile
you have JS
plus
ionic or
react native
for
VR you have
JS plus
react VR
for desktop application
you have JS
plus
electron
so if you
think about it if you were to
add JavaScript
with any of these things you can do
a lot of things
the part
where I mentioned that JavaScript is
nothing
JavaScript gives you nothing but logic
now suddenly this seems like
a super power because JavaScript
is nothing but logic so which means
I can mold it whatever
way I want to work it across any
domain I just need to choose
the right environment
but now a question pops into
my head
what exactly is it the environment
do
what exactly is it the environment do that
powers JavaScript in such a way
right so
what
exactly
is the
environment
do
or better word would be
exposes
or
yes
so how
exactly is it able to do that
it basically exposes
some sort of methods
methods or
functions
and where exactly are these
let me instead of
this it would make
a lot more sense it basically
exports functions
right so these environment
have predefined functions like
browser give you some sort of function
that you can utilize using JavaScript
and make use of it
and make your work to
develop front end apps
node gives you some function that you could utilize
using JavaScript and
develop back end apps likewise
it basically exposes
function now the question is how
how exactly is it happening all
of this happens
because of something called
objects
which is why it is like go
to statement to say
JavaScript is nothing
without objects because
objects powers everything
in JavaScript no matter what you were
to name across any
of these things be it
be it
browser node ionic
react native react via
electron all
of this eventually boils down
to some random function
in a
object right
so just a quick show of hands if everyone is
aware what object is what object
data structure is by now I think you
all would be knowing but just checking
you all know right
I know Dheeraj knows that
that is for sure what about
others
Abhinav Varun
Ashish, Shabhishek, Muniswara
Hemangi, Ashwini, Raja,
Rita, Sahil, Kiran
Shashank we all know right
correct it is nothing
but key value pair so
functions on a object
this is how your typical object
looks like everything in between
is an object as long as it is a key
value pair right so
functions
on an object are called methods
on
objects
are
called
method
this is very important
people don't know
this key what is the difference
in between function and method all
functions are method
but not all methods are functions
if you understand what I mean
sorry it is the other way around
all methods are functions but not all functions
are methods because for
it for a function to be a method
it needs to be present on
object body so suppose
you have
who
something written
like this
and you have an object
inside of it
you have who written
right
so in this particular case
who will be our
method in this case it is a
simple function
right
no no
nothing much we were just covering up
whatever we covered in the last class
okay
so with that now
let us go
now that I have told you
this everything in
JavaScript is possible because of
objects and whatever
information is moved across
what exactly the environment brings in
for JavaScript it brings in
some sort of object and some
methods available in an object for JavaScript
to utilize them right
so now I have told you this
but now let us go and get some
solid proof right
so
let's go to
the code base so
first of all is my screen
is the text
big enough yes
great
so here
if you remember in the last class what we did
was I simply console
document is basically a type of
document
likewise I did window is basically
an type of
window right we know for
a fact that whatever DOM
manipulation we had learned in the
last class basically
class 11
if you remember if I were to open
the questions also
as you solve them you could see all of
these things were present
isn't this how you access
an object using the dot
notation likewise
if I were to open
here and check here you could see
document is basically an
object window is basically
an object so this is a big thing
so if window is basically an object
window is a top most thing
even above document
it is here so which means key
everything inside everything
that you know of on this
particular web page is
available on this
object so would you all agree
with me key everything is an object
especially when we're talking about front end
development yes
great
so with that
now let us go through
the last
question
that we solved
question number one it was
a very simple question that we solved let
me try
opening it
here
let me just see
this is what we had
developed in the last class
right
if I were to click on hello
more dom notes are getting added
as you could see here also
if you see
focus here more dom
notes keep on getting added as
I click on this right now
wait build it
back then now let us go
and exactly break
down key what exactly is happening
right so
if you remember what we did we had a
selector which again
by the way is present on
document so document is something
which is again present on window
so if I were to go here
and do window dot document
it would still select
if I do document it would still
select so basically this is like
a shorthand instead of this I could have
written window dot document
and it would have
other window is not defined
because initially window is not defined
but document is there so
you can simply go ahead and do document dot
query selector and
once again document is something which
is given to you by an environment
which environment a browser environment
in this particular case and
you are able to select element
so this again query selector
can you tell me whether query selector is
a function or a method
method method method
correct correct so it is a method
it is not a function because it is present on
an object called document
right now
let me
even though we were not using
this event I have shown you back then
let me write a
function here
just a second
let me write a
declare a function cost handler
is equal to
something like this
and inside of this I will move the
this particular
logic
and
now think of it this way
what exactly is the structure
of query
sorry add event listener
so this
document dot query selector this also
must have returned something in
that we are storing in detail element
right but if you
focus here here also we are using
the dot notation so which means
here also it must be
given some sort of object only
so some object is stored in btn
element that we
are accessing on that object
we have something called add
event listener present and that
takes two things
it basically takes
an event
and it takes a
callback right
so whatever is the definition if you were
to go to mdn you would
find something like this only
this
document dot query selector
returns an object that you can store in
a variable and you can attach
an event listener on it
by saying that for this
particular event whenever this event is
noticed in this btn element
just do call this function
so what we did
was we did this
and how do I know
what exactly was the event fired
so which is why it also
passes in that particular callback
it gives me an event
which I think we saw in the last
class also but
let me simply console it here
and now you would see
when I click here I am getting an
event right so this event
tells me everything
this event again by the way is an object
as you could see there is a key value pair
correct
so now think about it like this
whatever you may be
whatever you may want to know about this
particular event
what actually happened on your web page
someone clicked right
all possible thing
is mentioned here
so
so one of the things
as you could see here
here it says alt key
here it says
alt key is false
but here it says alt key is true
all I did was by
clicking I also pressed on the
alt key
this should tell you that
this gives you so much information
that what actually has happened
now you can imagine whenever someone
was copying test and they were doing
easy you could put a check for it
if they are pressing this particular key
and
let's say they are pressing the alt key
or in this particular case control key
you can say
the user wants to copy
so these are all tools which are made
available to you now
it must be starting to making sense
what exactly this event is all about
event gives you something called target
and
it gives you
basically all sort of information about
this particular component
this particular tag and
what exactly was
the keystroke all about
right
and I can
simply put this handler
in here since
I am not using anything
the event I can
ignore it and if I click on it
it is still working
right
so that is the
best part about
JavaScript
right
so now would you agree with me when I say
everything in JavaScript is an object
now that
we have seen some solid proof as well
cool
now let me
close this and tell you what
we will be doing now
for this particular class we just have to
solve these three problems that's it
we will be solving these three problems
and to solve these three problems
we need to learn something
no
we were just getting started with the meaty
part of the lecture now
actually you are right on time
cool
so now
all we have to do is
call
solve these three problems
so let's focus on question one
so the way that we will be moving forward now
is that we will see this problem
then we will try to
solve it one way then we will learn
something new and then
you need to help me solve it
the new way
does that work
I hope everyone
is able to follow
this
right
Abhinav, Ankit, Abhishek
the pace and all is ok right
Chinmay, Dheeraj,
Brahmod, Pradeep, Himangi
Sambet
Shambhu Raje
great great great
cool then
let's get started with the
problem then
ok
so
let me open the problem
here first
let me make it two
ok
so initial thoughts I see
there is a remove all button at the top
and there are n number of tasks here
and with a delete option present
with them
right so it looks more or less
like a to do list
correct it looks like a
to do list and we somehow need to make it work
let's go through the problem statement
first so there are two things
that we need to do first
make all button works
all remove all button so
idea is when I click on this
the entire thing should be
removed right so this
is the first thing
and the second thing is also
make individual delete button
work ok so when I click
on this delete right now nothing is happening
but when I click on this
when I click on
let's say this button
this entire li should be
disappeared not that this should
be disappeared so
ok
great so
what would be the brute force way of
solving it
let's start with the first one
remove all button so I
think oh the idea is present here
already I can most probably
target
this id and
on click of this button I can simply
remove
the ul tag
this we can do display none
also but if you
want to remove it completely from your
DOM then in that case
a method
is provided to us remove
right so this
time we won't be relying on
CSS instead we will be relying
on these objects
JavaScript methods which are
given to us through events and
all cool
great yeah
so easy stuff
I know the first part is at least
easy so
we will be needing your help now
the idea is all how
can I target this button what should I write
here anyone
what should I write here
here
select query
no
there is nothing called select query
talking about
JavaScript select query is not there
correct Rita
we can use query
selector and get element
by id so Ashish
so I think there was a type on
your end instead of select query I think you
wanted to write query selector
correct but
one thing that
Rita miss was this is an id
so you cannot actually use
.btn instead
as Ashish
you need to use hashtag
right and since you were doing
query selector it won't work
also that way
great anyway
so let me
just write it down
then so all I
need to do is remove
all btn is
equal to query
selector is available on document
object so I can do
document.query selector
and since we are targeting
id I can simply
this
now if I go to console
console
remove all button
you would see I am
finding the button here
so I am able to target it
it looks like a tag because that is how
the browser is showing it to you but in
reality it is nothing but
an object
right it is nothing but
.getElementId
also
work right yes
getElementId
would also work
so now that
I have this with me
so which means I can
now use methods which are available
on this particular object
to remove it right
but what exactly is it that we want to
remove
remember we discussed whenever the user
is using this I ideally want to remove
this whole ul so maybe
I can somehow target a ul as
I can see there is only one ul
I can simply
write it like this const
all items is equal to
document.query
selector
and here I can say
ul because there is only
one ul so it would definitely
work in my favor
and I can simply use
remove all btn dot
addEventListener
so this again is
a method which is available on
all btn method
all btn
object in here if
you remember we need to pass event
and callback
right so I can
go and say
I can go
here and say
delete
an event
using
JavaScript
it mentions remove
method
and here also if you focus
here it says method not function
so this is the key
difference but now I think
it all makes sense
so simple thing
event is going to be
click and callback
is going to be
do we need to use
event here
right now I don't think there is any need for event right
so all I can do is go
here and say
all items dot
remove
would it work yes or no
how many of you say it would work
ok
let's see
if it works
right
so congratulations
it is working
so
the first part is done
now comes the second part
now this is
a bit tricky because
if you think about it
up until now we had this
button and on click of this we simply
had to delete this
ul tag right which I
targeted here but now I
either have to put
this id
on each of these
button because how else
an id on this l i
otherwise how else would I know
which of these delete button
was clicked
which of these delete button was clicked
and on click of these
delete button which
this thing I had to delete
ok
now
there is no reset
possible once removed Kabir
you need to add it on your own
ha
Ashish that is right
so that is one way of doing things
you can put id on each of the element
each of the l i element
but my question is
do you think
that is the ideal way to go forward
how about others what do you think
I will go forward
I put one id on this button
one id on l i
one id on this button one id on l i
here you have four
but you could potentially have
10, 20, 30, 40
I think we can
index ok
we can also use
query selector
all that is also one way to do
you can use class
yes you can use class
but if you were to use class
on click of this l i tag
this delete button
how would you know which class
which l i with that
particular class you had to remove
so there is a problem
and the problem no matter what solution
we find
it is going to be more or less a hacky way
of solving things
so what is the
best practice
when you come across this problem
so first of all let us talk about
brute force approach
which is still somewhat good
right
so let's
do that
so we will remove
all button for now
and all I am going
to do is to const
all btns
or let's say all
del btn
all delete button
is equal to
document dot
query selector all
how can
I target these buttons
I can simply do
ul
it would target
everything
so if I were to console
all del
button
sorry
btn
all del
btn you would see it has
given me four buttons
right now
wanted
we can do parent remove
ok so kiran is
definitely onto something here
kiran says if I were to
click any of this button
I can remove its parent
right and
if I were to go with that logic
it would make perfect sense
why because for each of these
if you remember from our last class
we learned no matter a parent
can have multiple children
but each of those children
will have only one parent and that
is exactly what we want here
so what we want to do on click
of any of these button
I need to delete their parent
so tell me
what should I google
how to get
parent
element
for any
how to get
parent for any element
in javascript
ta ta ta
ok
you get
parent node
since we are using note list
it is going to be parent
node in our case
so which means if we were to go
ahead with kiran's logic
all we have to do on click of any of these
buttons I had to remove
this li basically
the parent of this button
that makes sense
correct I hope everyone is following
yes
so let us
go ahead and
so which means we still have to
add event listener to each one of them
so let's do that
let me do for let i
is equal to 0
i is less than or del
btn
dot length
and do i
plus plus that's it
right and inside of this
we can
say
all del
btn i
dot
add event listener
what is the event that we are
listening for click
and I need to write a
call back here
and in this call back
I can simply say
this button
there is another method which is available
parent
node
dot
remove
right so this
loop will go on and
it will add event listener
on total of 4
elements
right now
it somewhat makes sense let's go and test
it out if I click
this task to only this
should be deleted let me
open elements also
and expand I am going
to click on this del button
and there is only one parent let's see
it works so
thank you for suggesting that
it works I am able to date
individual elements and I can
remove all also right
so we are able to solve the first
problem now my question
to you is
though it works do you think
it is the best solution out there
considering that we have to attach
event listener on each of those buttons
think
it true tell me
do you think it is the best solution
right now there are 4 buttons
but what if there were 10 buttons
you had a web page or let's say
you are building a form there you could have
potentially 10, 15, 20 buttons
even though your JavaScript
web page would still be able to handle it
but each of those buttons is doing some heavy operation
right so which means
it would all eventually catch up
can you explain
query selector ql
ok
we will do that just some later on
so before that just wanted
to conclude this even though
it works it is not the best solution
because on each
of those nodes you have to
add an event listener
each of these buttons maybe
it could have been helpful
if and only
if you could add just one
event listener click
not many just one
and that one event listener would take care
of the entire thing
no matter which button you click it should work
right wouldn't that be the best
thing wouldn't that be the best solution
you are
able to
achieve the functionality
you are not overpopulating your
DOM with n number of
event listener but there is only one
right
so that is something
that we will be implementing in a while
but before that let me revisit
line number
this
so basically Arun
if you were there in our class number
11 we discussed query selector all
it is a way of selecting the element
from the DOM right
so remember how you write CSS
how do you select this
button if you were to
you could have written li
the button you could have written any of those
you cannot directly write button because
that CSS would be applied to this button also
line number 12 which you don't want
so you explicitly want to say
all the button which is present
inside of ul
so for that to say I have written
element like this so whenever you write query selector
you can write things like this
right otherwise
think of it like
you are writing CSS selector
only basically you have to write CSS
selector only here
cool
so now that we have established
even though this works
there is still a better solution out
there so now let us go ahead and try
and figure out what that solution is
and how we are going to make
it work right and this
by the way is a classic example of
polymorphism that you may have heard
of in object oriented programming
there are multiple ways of doing one thing
this also works
but this is not the ideal solution
so we are going with another
solution now which is the ideal one
and it works
so
just a second
before
that
let me
so there is
something called
event bubbling
how many of you
have heard of this thing
event bubbling
now
we will get to it
so
let us quickly see
if event
that we are getting in the callback
maybe that would be able to help us
so what the idea is
I will be I will not be including
the
add event listener on each of these things
instead what is the common
parent of all of
these buttons
what is the common
parent for all of these buttons
is it D tag
allied tag dual tag
out of these three which is the common
parent
so
UL is the thing
luckily we have selected
UL here
so we will be
attaching the event listener on
UL
add event listener
and
event listener takes
in two things
first it takes the event then it takes
the
then it takes
it takes
it takes the callback
correct
ally can be right to
no ally will not be right why
because this ally is a parent of
this button but I cannot use
the same ally for this button
right because ally is different
so UL is the common parent
right
so let us
go ahead and
write the code for this now all we have to
do is the event is
definitely going to be clicked as you
had seen here also
and now we need
to have some sort of callback and
in this callback I will be getting
an event this by the way
again just a reminder this
is just an
argument so name
can be anything I can change this to
and it would still work
so but the common practice
across is you either use
E or you use event
right
we are concerned with event
now let me quickly see
is event giving me something
which I can use to target
which button was clicked
right
so
I have
event let's go to console
do this okay
okay they both
look alike but if I were to
go down
and select the target
when I hover over this target you see
task two is getting selected
but when I hover over
this target task one is getting selected
so which means this works
event gives me a way of
identifying which of these buttons is
and right now I only have one add event
so which means I am definitely going in the right
direction that is for sure
so now let us go ahead
and
do something here
so I know for a fact that
in this callback event
which by the way again is an object
nothing else
JavaScript may sound complicated but
everything boils down to object
event is an object and
I can simply store
the delete button
you could say directly here
right I can say
const
lm is equal to
event.target
right and
just to prove it to you I can even say
lm name is
equal to
event.
tag name
and I can
console
name so if I were to go here you see
it is getting
undefined maybe it is
named something else
sorry sorry
this again
event.target
inside of it I would be having the name
so
see we are getting button
so which means
I am able to identify
now all I have to do is pretty simple
I need to copy this
function that I had written
paste it here and
change this to
lm that's it I can remove
the name by the way
now if I were to save this go here and do
this
I am able to delete
right
so which
way was better the first
one or the second one
keep in mind that we added one
event listener here in here
we added two event listeners
sorry one event listener here we added four
here we added one so which one was
better first or second
which one do you think
was better
which one do you think was better
but unnecessary clicks also getting
fired correct that is fine
clicks
let me tell you this key
in javascript
in future classes you will learn about this
then it would make a lot
more sense
there is something called a main thread
you will study this I think
as the some of the last
classes of javascript you will learn
about this and it is pretty interesting
when you learn about the JS architecture
in detail what exactly is
event clue what is callback queue
what is the speed at which
javascript actually processes
right so
you will get your answer
in that class Ashwini
I don't want to overwhelm you
with it right now but just to
give you a brief idea no matter
what you do javascript is
processing continuously
right it is processing continuously
the main thread is never free
it is just that it is
always doing something but it makes time for
these events these events are the easiest
thing for main thread to
manage right
I hope
sorry I think screen share is most important
screen visible
so I hope
Ashwini that answered your question
without saying
much
right
cool
so there is one tiny problem with this
solution there is one
tiny problem that even though
I click on this task
it is getting
removed if I click on task
4 it is getting removed
so can you tell me why is that happening
any idea
that is happening because
your event whenever
you correct
the parent is still the same because
the parent is still the same and you haven't
explicitly said that
on click of what
on li
all items
basically is
basically
all items basically is the
entire thing
so if you click
anywhere if you click anywhere
we will
learn about it in the second question in detail
the event basically bubbles
to the top
so event was generated here
but it bubbles to the top to
UL right
which is why even if you click
anywhere be task
2 be task 1 it will
go up and while
going up it applies to you
so do you think of a way
we could put some sort of
a check
if only this delete was
clicked not the entire thing
anywhere but only delete
so
do you think there is a way
to somehow know the
tag name
is there a way
to know the tag name because
if I were to click here we would
be giving up we
would be getting a p tag
right but if I were to click on
this button I would be getting a button
tag correct actually
if you remember we
had done it like this const
tag name is equal
to lm.
tag
name and I can
simply put a check here
in simple English language
if tag name
is equal to
button then
remove
otherwise
do
right so when I save this
go ahead do this and come
back here and
just for testing
purpose I will
include
this also
so when I click on task two
event is fired as you could see
event was fired and
the callback function was called but
since it was p tag
this condition failed
and parent didn't get removed
but when I click
on delete button
it got removed
delete button it got removed
so this to me
seems like a
better solution than this
right
any queries here
any queries for this part
this question
we saw the brute force approach
we learnt about
event basically holds
the entire thing
no matter what you want to know
even right now
it would make a little bit more sense when I say
event holds all the data
that you could possibly need to make a decision
right
so anyone
is there anyone who
is it clear to everyone
should we move forward to question two
yes
Abhinav, Vanket, Abhimanyu
Abhishek, Arun
Ahmed, Ashwini, Ashish
Dheera, Srimangir, Muniswara, Pradeep
Pramod, Shaikh, Sambit, Rita
Vinay, Upendra, Tejan, Rohesh
Shambhu, Rajesh, Ashank
all able to follow right
let's move on
let us up the level a bit
and now we will talk about
question two
so let me change it here
also
question two
okay
we have a button called double
that's it
HTML also just says double
with something called double
holder
so there are two things that we have to do here
two things that you have to do here
first, click the button
that is destroyed
but two new buttons
are created in its place
the next two buttons should behave like
the above button
okay
so the idea is
key
on click of this button
this button will be destroyed and
a copy of this button
would be created
so there would be two buttons
so when I click on this button again
this button again
another button gets made
so basically it would be
like an exponential thing
it will keep on going
so we are
deleting something also
and then
in place of that thing
we are having
two more buttons
in that place
okay
so
before we solve this
let us go ahead
and let me create a file here called
bubbling.js
so let us quickly go through
what exactly bubbling is
and using this concept
bubbling concept
I will be solving this question number two
so I will tell you what bubbling is
and then you need to help me solve
this question too because
it seems tricky
so I will be needing your help
cool
so let us go ahead and
do that
okay
so go to
event bubbling
what I am going to do
is I will
write
let us say
div
class
could be
box and
grandparent
then we have another div
here
class would be
logs and parent
then we have another div
here will be
class will be
box
and child
so we have three divs
one side of another
something like this
and I will also mention the name
grandparent
parent
and child
okay
let us go ahead
let me open this also
so you can see how it looks like
okay
right now it looks like this
sort of E
let's make it a bit better
by adding some styles
to it
right
so first of all
I will be adding a style for
boxing one
sorry
you can say border is
one pixel solid
gray
then we will have
grand
parent
this would be parent
and
this would be
child
okay
so grandparent we could have background color
set to let's say
light blue
and some
width
and
height is 20
and I will copy paste this
across
only thing
change the color
this would be
light green
and this would be light
light golden yellow
okay
and
grandparent is at top
so I will make this one as
10 this one as
5 now let's go ahead
okay
so now it looks like this
so
this is better
you ask me
so what is it that I
want to build here
or what is it that I want to
demonstrate here
so we have
grandparent here
let me
add a
script tag
at the end
mentioning const
gp is
equal to document
dot query
selector
dot grand
parent right
and I can here say
gp
dot
add
event listener
click
and here I will be getting
console dot
log click
tick
so now if I were to
open console
here you would see if I click
on grandparent
I get clicked which is
expected right
but if I were to click on parent
I again get clicked
why because parent
is inside of
grandparent so essentially
grandparent is getting clicked
right and if I were to click on
child it again
shows it was clicked
now my question to you is if
every time it is showing
it was clicked
how can I possibly know
which of these elements was clicked
whether the grandparent itself was clicked
or one of the
child element was clicked
how can I be sure of it
here
it's not like I
can somehow discern on the
basis of tag name because here
all the three have tag name
as dip so I cannot
go through that path also
so shouldn't
there be a way
that I can tell
whether grandparent was clicked
or basically
whether the grandparent was clicked
or someone inside of it was clicked
yes or no that only makes
sense right something from
event must be different
correct so now you are
catching up
in which direction
my conversation is going
so now let us go
ahead and let
me print the event
right
and in this event
I will have two things
I will have something called target
and I will
something called
current target and this
is a
this thing out there I can do
event or target we know this
using this so far event or target
gives me the target element that was
clicked but there is
something called event dot
current target
it also gives me something so now
let's go and see what it does
when I click here
both target is set to box
grandparent and current target
is set to box grandparent
when I click parent
now this
is where it gets interesting
right now you see
the difference right when I clicked on
parent my target is set to
box parent but my current target
is set to box
grandparent
right so
when I click on child what
do you think will be the target and current
target when I click on child any guesses
remember child is inside of
parent
when I click
on child what will be the target
and current
target
target is child correct
and current target is grandparent
correct correct
right so current target
is basically all
about where the event listener was
added
right wherever the event listener
was added
that will be the current target and
target is going to be the actual
element that was clicked
right and how does my grand
parent eventually the
event when I click on this child
element your javascript
will see that no event listener is
attached on this day right
so
it will bubble it will keep on
going up
inside of this child
outside of it
the parent is this way so
event bubbles and go to this
is any event listener added here
yes or no no so it would bubble from
here also then it reaches
this grandparent
is the event listener added here
yes it is
added so this becomes the
current target
now are you
able to follow why
events are so important
events give you whole lot of information
that you could play around with
right
I hope the pace
and all is ok
so that's why last question clicking
deleted button correct
the pace and all is
ok right everyone is able to follow
why if you are not able to follow let me know
now
yes
ok
so
through this
I can tell what a current
target is and what is the target
so let me go here and
google as well
target vs
current
target someone here
must have done a good job at
discerning between them
current target
tells us
on which element the event was attached
that is happening in our case
or the element whose event
listener triggered the event
in our case it is grandparent
so which is why the first half is making sense
to us right
and the second part event.target tells us
where the event started
so this is the main part
current target tells us
on which element
the event listener was attached
to or which
element the event actually
was triggered
current event.target tells us
where actually the event started
so is the difference
between target and current target
clear to everyone
yes
great
so now
this was my hint to you
let me rename it
target
current target
so now
I will go back to
question 2
so now using
that knowledge you should
help me in solving
this problem right
but we will solve it after a quick break because
we have been going on for almost one hour
we have covered a lot
in the last one hour
so lets take a break, stretch your legs
go for a walk, have some water
and when you will be back then we will start solving
question number 2
using what we just learned
cool
so lets go for a break
for it is
10 0
it is 10 08
we will be starting with at
10 13
right
we will be starting at 10 13
go for a break
now while everyone is away
if any one of you has any doubt
regarding anything that we have covered so far
now is the time to ask
anyone has any doubt
regarding anything
I hope everyone is saving to follow though
but
sometimes in loop we do
event or target and sometimes we
go by array 1
to target the element, what is the difference
so the difference
I will share it on the whatsapp group also
in detail, you could read about it
there is something called html collection
and then there is something called
node list, so whenever we use
something like query selector
it gives us a node list
but when I use something like get element by
id or something like that
it sort of gives us
the html collection
so I have a very good
article in mind, I will share
it with you, so you can
use that
that should be able to help
for most of the problem
that we are doing array i
you could do the other one also
both ways are fine
it's not that one way is better than
the other one, both ways are equally fine
so you will see
that in the article that I will share
on the whatsapp group after this class
any other doubts
any other doubts anyone
also
I would say
try to post your questions
to everyone
so that everyone
knows
because like this particular question
was a very good question
no questions
and also
go have some water
and then we will continue in 3 minutes
you
one of the yesterdays
question
do share your
questions
over whatsapp
and look into it
what actually went wrong
ideally we can use either of the ways
and we can do it with
either of the things
ok
correct
sorry
cool then
it is 10.30
so let's begin
right
before we do is everyone back
just a quick yes no
yes
okay so four people are back that's for sure what about others are they not back
yet eight people are back or is it the same ten people eight people are back
okay here numbers are increasing gradually but eight people are back cool
so cool it's time to launch a poll right just to check if we'll play that game
again so the idea is the you should be able to balance it for both of the
options in poll right so let's see if you are able to do that as I mentioned
the last time also in none of the clubs anyone were able to do that so let's see
if you guys are able to do it or not right launching the poll again
oh shit close one
50 50 someone messed up someone messed up at the end see I told you it's almost
impossible for it to end with 50 50 cool then assuming not that everyone is back
we'll begin solving the problem at hand the problem at hand was question number
two where the idea was gone click off each of these button it should get
destroyed and on in place of that button we would be having another two buttons
and they would be in the exact same order so to destroy you know for a fact
which way to go right that is something that we are well versed with so let's go
ahead and simply start solving for it so I can see there is a parent so maybe
they could attach our event listener instead of the button but on the parent
because the second part says a two button should be exactly like the upper
button right so I like add the functionality to the parent right and on
click of that I'll delete this button first of all right so I'll be getting
target and current target so I'm thinking he may be what I can do is sir
on every click I will delete the target right I'll delete the target and then
from current target I will create two more buttons and append it to the
current target element does that make sense so I have a button and so I first
of all and this is inside a parent so first of all on click what I'm going to
this will be my target and this parent is going to be my current target so first
of all I know for a fact target is the button from which the event started so
I'll delete this target so this particular button would be deleted so
this would solve my one big problem he even if there are multiple buttons only
that button will be deleted from where the event started so that part is sorted
now post and all I have to do is simply create element if you remember from the
last class we created element so I'll create an element in that element I'll
create a div and I'll put it on current target right so my event listener will
be on parent right so it's the strategy clear should we code it out yes
cool so at least it is clear to five force let's go ahead and put it out and
in case you see I am going somewhere wrong we need to interject and help me
correct it right so first thing first since we are putting the event listener
on parent I know I see key event listener has an ID value right so what
I'm going to do is I will say const double oh my bad double holder is equal
to document dot query selector and query selector is fine go to at this point
only selector is good right this makes sense because there's an ID I put
hashtag in case this was class I would have put dot exactly how you do in CSS
selectives right and in this double holder dot add event listener this gives
me which again need an event that is click and we will be needing a callback
because we our strategy is to play around with target and event sorry
current target so which means key we need to access event in here oh event in
here right and so first thing that we are going to do is let me create first
button can you help me in creating first button in document which function is
used to which method sorry is used to create an element what should I write
here we did it in the last class character create element and what
element are we looking out to create we are looking to create a button element
so which is why I will write button there right and we need to make it
exactly like this one so which means key class also needs to be added here which
the class name is double so let's add that so I'll say first button dot inner
text is equal to double non-double a but double and we can say first button dot
set attribute what attribute are we setting class what are we setting it to
double right so now you see whatever we learned in the last class we are now
using it here just actually because it just makes sense so likewise I'll create
the second button also all I have to do is to second button right so now I have
two button place and what I can do is I can append it right if you remember we
can append right there is something called append so we will be appending
this on double holder so I can simply say double holder dot append append
let's append the first button first sorry it is going to be like this and
then second button and once you are able to do that all I have to do is even dot
target dot right so let's see if it works movement of truth it's working
right every time I click that button gets deleted and it is creating two
buttons in that place I want to test one thing right now we only have a button
here when I click three buttons are here when I click the middle one you see when
I click the middle one two buttons were created when I click the last one when I
click the first one two buttons keeps on getting added at the end right it
deletes this button and two buttons get added at the end right so this solves
the second problem also right what's this clear to everyone yes now at this
point I think it would all seem a bit trivial only right give I can you button
create Kanna higher element create gonna let me do it you want to change the
inner text you want to set attributes to it let me do it it's pretty straight
forward at this point I assume right now I think you should be somehow getting a
picture key by events play such an important role in dom manipulation at
least right he what exactly is it he events get this much value right event
object which contains the entire story it sort of gives you a story in short
form right he what was clicked what else was clicked back then is it is it target
is it currently target for what is the state of that button right now all of
those things is presenting with this one object all you have to do is go through
it and it will give you so many methods to play around with right cool so if
it's clear to everyone they can move forward to the big question now q3 if is
it clear then yes so let's move on to the third question now and this is a
big one right as you push the text present here right this is the question
implement key taps such that on pressing one you scroll to section one let me open
it first here q3 implement key taps such that on press of one press one to go to
section one press two to go to section there must be somewhere written is there
section two
the section two is there take section two section three there in total three
sections got it so the idea is key you now need to listen to keyboard events
now this is interesting and B if you were to press B you should go jump
directly to the bottom of the page if you press one you should jump to
section one right so through anchor tag you may have learned to do this during
your HTML classes but now we are listening to keyboard events right so
this would be interesting let me make another file first called keyboard dot
HTML right we will be talking about keyboard events in this one and it
should help you key say event and line example obviously and in here what I'm
going to have is
let's say input right and type would be
text
and
we could have a div here side of it we could have a span right and say key is
pressed and for this particular span I could say class is equal to key press
this is just so I'm able to target it easily and likewise I could probably
have a div here right and for this one I can say rest right
inside of this I could have a span saying shift is pressed right and what I
can do is add a class here called shift T so let me write T script tag for this
now so the idea is now what I want to show you guys is that whenever any
keyboard is keys pressed how would you make out key whether C was pressed or
some numeric key was pressed or whether control P was pressed command P was
pressed so now we are moving towards that direction right so once you are
able to figure that out all we have to do is solve this one big problem and then
we can call it a day. So let me open a new tab here and I'll call this keyboard
keys pressed shift is pressed something is happening but now let us go and write
some Java script first right so let me say input oh sorry I need to take it
first input.document.add event listener what event am I listening to oh sorry
not event listener query selector I'm looking for input right likewise let me
have
key press this is going to be dot key press and this one is going to be shift
press dot shift so what I'm going to do now I'll create a input dot add event
listener and in this event listener I'm going to write two things so first I'm
going to measure here key press by the way so far we've been mostly playing
around with this thing click events right but this is link on MDN event
reference it gives you all possible types of events mentioned in here right
so let me share this link and you can go through this through this link after the
class and it mentions all of the possible events which are available in
JavaScript which you could probably mention in add event listener right so
you prefer to go through them and play around right that is just for your
reference now let's focus here and now this keypress obviously I'll be getting
let me just do that console dot log
rest right so now let's go here okay dark console when I do I'm going to
type scalar SCALER this I know for sure key on input key press event I'm
getting some data up until now we were getting on pointer events now I'm going
to write event here and I'm going to say event right so every time with each key
press I'll be getting an event also let me say yes now this is the interesting
part up until now you are getting pointer event because those events were I was by
clicking so I was sort of using a mouse or the pointer but now I am using my
keyboard right so which is I'm getting keyboard event here if you see I'm also
getting the key code as key S but here in this case keys S right so which
means key I get a keyboard event also and through this I can tell key what
exact key was pressed right right now here you could see there must be
somewhere written shift now here is say shift as false I'll close it and this
time I'll do shift S it is capital right this time you'll see it says key as S
and shift key was set to true now do you understand key how does your browser
know key whether they whether on shift anything any shift anything why do they
have to enter a capital letter not a small letter how do they get to number
of someone must have configured it that way right so this is how it is
configured actually so someone internally is listening okay shift key
was also pressed S key was also pressed so if simply S key was pressed so which
means we are talking about small s in case we press shift and S then we are
talking about capital S so someone must have configured it that way
and believe it or not all of no matter what big application you pick be it
google.com Facebook Instagram scalar dashboard also everything is built up
on this tiny concepts that you are learning right so isn't it interesting
these are the actual building blocks for these right it again gives me the
target it gives me the source element it basically I'm getting this key so this
is the main thing right now I can update also right because I have key press in
this so maybe what I'm going to do is say key press dot inner
inner inner text open why is it not showing key press dot target why is it
not showing inner text we've been using inner text right
why is it not showing is event triggered yes event is triggered
inner text is working not sure why it is not showing up here but inner text is
working so now I'm going to update it like this key on key press I removed
that event
on key press I'll pick the key so I can say key press dot inner text is equal to
key is event dot key event dot key and I could also have shift press I can put a
condition here key if event dot shift press if it is true then it will be
pressed otherwise it would be not pressed tick now let's test it out by
default it is saying pressed for both
because here it says
key is like this okay I'm going to say s oh sorry I can remove this
I can say yes key says shift is not pressed now I'm going to say scalar
with capital C is it shift press only enough or something else console dot
log event let's see it is shift key shift key is set to true event dot shift
key yes see see it's working a L E R so it is working with every keystroke I'm
getting a keyboard event and from that keyboard event I am able to tell key
what character whether he was pressed or not whether the shift key was pressed
or not what is the key right so I'm able to do all of these things in the event
that I'm getting and I'm able to type this right so it's interesting right now
I can listen to not just wonder events but I can also listen to keyboard events
now this opens a whole new door for me is huh okay so just again take it so
likewise not just keep this you would have similar events like this available
on some there are multiple events present there is key press key down key
up and they mean exactly what you think they mean right so basically key presses
when an actual event is pressed key down the event is fired when you keep when
the key is still down right and key up is when it is left up so when the key
goes up on that point the event is fired key press and key up more or less work
the same way right but yes
key press cool then so is it clear to everyone was everyone able to follow
till here no doubts or is there anyone who has any doubts till here anything
you think I would be good to cover Opendra, Vinay, Shaikh, Abhinav
all right video breaking question seven from last class need this correct so
question seven from last class need this and now you know how to solve question
seven from last class is the video breaking us we just have one more one
question to solve so let's power through the video still breaking let me turn off
my camera it would definitely help take let me know if the video quality
improves was breaking a little bit was past tense so is it fine now now good
great great great great then so now for this problem so what is what was the
problem the problem is simple when you press key one what was the problem so
when we press one we should skip to section 1 when we press 2 which will
skip to section 2 when we press press 3 we should go to this when you press T we
should go to the top of the page and when we press B we should go to the
bottom of the page right so which means key we simply have to listen to certain
events we could put an event listener on h1 I'm thinking we can listen to
these events and if it matches any of these things will take them to the
respective places where they want to go right and to scroll basically there is a
method which is available on this thing called IDs are given right so we need to
have something for these IDs ticket we need to have something for these IDs and
there is something called scroll into view scroll into view so what does it
say the elements interface score interview methods scrolls the elements
ancestor container such that the element of score interview is visible to the
user so this is what we want so what we want is key when I press one this is in
my viewport when I press 2 section 2 is in my viewport right so we will be using
this scroll into view for this so now let's go ahead and implement it so first
thing first I need to put a sector key various s1 s1 is basically my document
dot query selector since it must be having an ID so I'll put an ID called s1
likewise I'll make it for s2 and s3 need to change it here as well as to an s3
and now I need to add event listener so where should we add event listeners
considering key we are listening to event throughout considering we are
listening to even throughout so we can go ahead and add a div and listen
directly to window so I can say window dot add event listener so which means
key since we are adding the event listener on Windows so anywhere you click
as long as the window is focused anywhere you click we we should be able
to scroll basically this callback would work right and what event are we
listening for we are listening for key press and we are expecting a callback
here obviously and this callback will be getting an event now we need to use this
event so I'll need to say let key is equal to event dot key right now let me
just console dot log key now let's go to the page go to console clear here if I
press 1 2 3 anything I'm doing as you could see I am getting the key correct
so far so good we are we are halfway there now all I have to do is use this
scroll into view this is how it's used it's called into view it it again is a
method so which means key you need to add the element in front of it which
element s1 s2 s3 so are we need to write it something like s3 dot scroll
interview s2 dot scroll interview cool so let me check the type of these things
I'll go back here I'll press 1 now we are getting string so this is a very
common mistake that people do key since you are getting a string people while
writing condition they put triple equal to and put it there so which means key
it does a hard check so it doesn't find any matches right so let us now write
it if key is triple equal to one focus that I put it on in quotes right I want
to do s1 dot scroll into view cool and save it now let us go and see if it
works right I am on section 2 I am going to press 1 and it works right right
everyone followed right how we got to this it's interesting right
Arun, Nehmat, Abhimanyu, Abhinav, Ankit, Chinmay, Dheeraj, Hemant, Munishwara, Pramod, Raja, Ramesh, Sheik, Vijay, Shashank, Vinay
I hope my screen is visible to all now all I have to do now all I have to do is
just keep on adding these condition for all the keystrokes which are mentioned
the question so one it's that secondly if I need to put a condition if key is
triple equal to 2 then in that case s2 dot scroll into view right else if key
is triple equal to 3 in that case s3 dots scroll into view right there is
something called tall sorry top and bottom as well so which means I'll
again check for if key is equal to B or just adding a double check if it is
equal to capital B essentially that typing bottom only so in that case I'll
write a different function window dot scroll to right so in window I'm saying
by scroll to zero document dot body dot scroll height right what does this do
let me copy this go here and I'll paste it don't paste code to depose that you
don't understand oh yeah I understand yeah
oh it's not letting me add code okay I'll type it window dot scroll to zero
comma document dot body dot scroll height see when I run this I got jump to
the bottom of the page right so basically what what am I saying here
I need to scroll to zero distance what is the starting point zero and how much
are we scrolling we are scrolling to body height so whatever is the body
height I will be able to scroll to that so body height obviously would be equal
to the entire thing so I would eventually be jumping directly to the
bottom open raise my screen clear I've zoomed the ID as well right cool so
likewise I can put somewhat the same logic for top also right else I can say
key is equal to T or key is equal to capital T case window dot scroll to zero
comma since we are scrolling to the top what is the distance we want to go far
away from top is it the entire body length no so what should I write here
crawl to says ki mujhe top se kitna dur jaana hai here I had mentioned ki mujhe
code top se body ki height jitna dur niche scroll karna hai now I want to stay at the top
so which means here from top I want to go zero far so which means key I have to
write it this way so now when I save this and I'll go here now I'm going to
press one two three let me you probably won't believe me you may think I've act
somehow so just to prove that I am legit I'm going to write key error so
right so you would see here the key also
okay I'm here I'm going to press one as you could see one was pressed right I'm
going to press two three if I were to press four nothing happened five nothing
happened any of this but when I press B sorry B I jump to the bottom when I
press T I jump to the top
Ankit is the screen not visible?
your caps lock is your caps lock is on I thought that you were shouting
now it's like here but you were able to follow right the demo part key how the
entire thing is working so we were successfully able to solve this question
as well correct
it's fine cool yeah so anyone has any doubt in this question interesting this
way we can make napa to scroll to say correct actually this is the way that
people do in big organization also this is the code that they write to make it
work one final dry run yes so in first of all what I did was I I had ID attached
to three sections so I was able to store it in these three element again I'm
storing objects the thing that we started this lecture with then on key
press I've put this event listener on window because I want to listen to the
entire no matter where the person click I want to listen to it so which is why I
had mentioned key press here now this event I'm receiving a keyboard event
from that keyboard event I'm extracting the key storing it in a variable called
key now we check the type of key it is always going to be a string it will
never be a number right so which is why I am doing a cross check for string one
two three four and for that we are using a function called scroll interview if
I'm not wrong in scrolling to view you can pass something called smooth also
yes there is called behavior and in behavior I can pass smooth let's try
that once I can again add an object here in here I can say behavior as smooth so
if I go back here and I scroll down when I press key one you see that smooth
behavior right so again it's nothing but object so I can do one two three you see
how smoothly it is scrolling here and there right and that was so easy you
just need to add a behavior to it right so which is why I say MDN is the golden
resource out there right all you have to do is go through MDN and you would find
it is such a golden resource correct cool yeah so I hope you guys found it
interesting today's class right that's all what I planned for today now in case
you have any doubt now is the time let me start the doubt solving session also
quick now if you have any doubt whatsoever now is the time what's the
scope when we put a listener to window what if we are typing somewhere else I
don't think it would well of your window should be in focus when I'm here and I'm
typing right now it is not showing but when I click here now my window is in
focus now when I type okay my bad need to console also
good so when I focus here and I'm typing SCALER it focused when I come here and
I type SCALER you see I'm typing here it is not focusing so as long as my window
is focused it is listening to those event when I click anywhere else it
won't if I come here and I type SCALER see it's not showing up here so which
means key my window needs to be focused because status where now when I click
back here SCALER cool right any other doubts regarding any any of the
questions that we had covered today be it keyboard events be target current
target event bubbling any of those things if you have doubts now is the
time anyone anyone has any question regarding anything
Abhinav, Ankit, Abhimanyu, Ahmed, Arun, Bhuvanesh, Chinmay, Dheeraj, Saraut, Hemant, Muniswara, Pradeep, Pramod, Rhea, Raja, Ramesh, Tejal, Lupendra, Vinay, Kiran, Shambhu, Rajesh, Ashank
no all good did no question because tomorrow class is going to be super
interesting tomorrow we will be integrating our very first API understanding
but overwhelming and the fact that you are finding it overwhelming is you are
on the right track it is supposed to be overwhelming but that is the journey
right from finding it overwhelming to finding it underwhelming so you're on
the right track shall we use click events to scroll to window shall we use
click events to scroll to window you can you can there's no problem with that but
that depends on the use case what is the use case you are solving for if the
product requires this then now you know key this is how you can achieve it but
why you should do it is up to you right
by the way tomorrow's lecture is going to be super interesting believe me 40 to
50 percent of your day-to-day tasks is integrating API's and tomorrow we will
be making call our very first API right we'll be building sort of a better app
tomorrow so do join it huh I'll share it on the
I'll share the for further reading for further reading I'll share some articles
current so I'll share this one there cool I hope you guys like the lecture
though and that's it I need any doubts or we can call it a day and once again
thank you for joining on a non-class day it means a lot please do please do
please do and in case you find any doubt whatsoever and kid feel free to
raise it within the first five minutes tomorrow right be on time raise it right
there and then I'll resolve your query there cool I'm good sounds like a plan
right great great great I need any doubts anyone any other doubts thank you
Pindra cool yeah I guess there are no other doubts but still I would urge all
of you to go through the recording complete your assignments and in case
you face any doubts feel free to visit on the whatsapp group discuss among
yourself the whole point of doing it as a cohort is you interact among yourself
right so discuss the questions among yourself and try to solve right so it's
it would be beneficial for everyone right and for any queries relating to
class bring your doubts tomorrow first time within the first five minutes we'll
talk it out cool with that I think we can call it a day right I have attached
the github link I'll be pushing the code now and you should be able to access it
right and for any other doubts you know where to reach me on whatsapp right
group right so with that going to today and ending the meeting now so I'll see
you all tomorrow thank you shake and bye bye everyone
you